<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the judge at the assizes held at Nottingham, on the 19th of July, 1689 by W. Wilson ...</title>
            <author>Wilson, W., Rector of St. Peter's Church in Nottingham.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12922587</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12922587</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66607)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 991:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the judge at the assizes held at Nottingham, on the 19th of July, 1689 by W. Wilson ...</title>
                  <author>Wilson, W., Rector of St. Peter's Church in Nottingham.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>vi, 7-31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Awnsham Churchill ..., and are to be sold by Joseph Howe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95428:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95428:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the JUDGE AT THE ASSIZES Held at NOTTINGHAM, On the <hi>19th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1689. By <hi>W. WILSON,</hi> M.A. Rector of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church in <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Awnſham Churchill</hi> at the Black Swan at <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Joſeph Howe,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Nottingham,</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:95428:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:95428:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Publication of this Diſcourſe is ſo far from being what was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when it was compos'd, that it is wholly owing to the importunate Friendſhip of ſome worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, (to whoſe Judgment I defer as much, as I value their good Eſteem;) who have perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me to take this Method to vindicate my ſelf from the Calumnies that ſome have loaded it with. When firſt I heard, that it was cenſur'd, I was not a little aſtoniſh'd, that after thoſe Days of Apprehenſion and Danger, in which we felt much, but fear'd more from that reſtleſs Party, who by too much influencing our Seats of Judicature in Cares of publick Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and leavening our Minds with that fierce and bitter Zeal, which does not only ſpoil the Pleaſure, but tends to deſtroy the very Being of Society; and giving us too plain and frightful a Demonſtration how ſerviceable our Diviſions are to their Deſign; a Diſcourſe of Juſtice, Mercy, and a true Zeal for the ſubſtantial Duties of Religion, and which above all
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:95428:3"/>was not only favoured with the Approbation of many Judicious Perſons, but particularly of that Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon, who upon the Bench expreſs'd an Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Regard to the great Duties it treat of, ſhould be accuſed and condemned by any that heart it. But not many Hours after it was preach'd, I was informed that it was attaqu'd with Severity enough; as if I had had little or no regard to the Honour of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> This dreadful Charge put me upon a ſearch, what that untoward Paſſage might be that had ſo unluckily eſcaped me, as to wound the Reputation of that Church, which I profeſs my ſelf not only to be a Member of, but highly to honour: But not being able to make the Diſcovery my ſelf, I was the more eaſily prevail'd upon to ſubmit it to the Judgment of the World. Is it not for the Honour of the Church, that all her Members ſhould <hi>do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, love Mercy, and walk humbly with their God?</hi> Or, that they ſhould expreſs a greater Zeal for theſe things, than for her Ceremonies? Is ſhe little beholden to thoſe that are deſirous ſhe had more Friends, and fewer Enemies; and eſpecially that thoſe that are and will be her moſt deadly Foes, had fewer advantages from among our ſelves to endanger, if not at laſt to effect her Ruine? Is it an Injury to her to be deſirous, that thoſe great and excellent Vertues, the want of which has once almoſt wounded her to Death, ſhould be more piouſly regarded by all her Children for the future, than (to the great ſatisfaction and benefit of none but Papiſts) has of late been by many of them? If the preſſing of theſe Things be my Fault, I own it; but am ſo far from repenting of it, that I bleſs God for the Opportunity I had to do it, But withal I muſt ſay, that it is neither for the Credit of my
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:95428:3"/>Reprehenders, nor the Churches Honour, to have the inculcating theſe things paſs for a Reflection upon her. For, which the Church is moſt beholden to, thoſe that conſider her Ceremonies, as ſhe her ſelf does, as ſuch indifferent things as may upon juſt Cauſes be altered and changed, or they who would have the World believe, that the Church does regard them as Matters as unalterable, and conſequently as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as the <hi>doing Juſtice, and loving Mercy?</hi> they who ſay that they are not to be eſteemed equal with God's Law, or they who by quarrelling with thoſe that ſay ſo, as Enemies to the Church, do ſeem to intimate, that they are perſuaded the Church does believe they are? In a word, they who are perſuaded that the Religion of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is that great and noble Things, that approves it ſelf to the Reaſon of Mankind, or they who make it ſo mean a thing as can gratify no more than our Senſes, does not need any great depth of Judgment to determine. For I am confident, that no one that reads this Diſcourſe without Prejudice and Partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, will think the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Honour in the leaſt concern'd in any thing delivered in it; but will be tempted to believe, that they who have charged it thus fooliſhly, have no other Religion but what is made up of Ceremony. And if they be ſuch that are offended at it, they, I will own, have ſome reaſon for their diſlike; becauſe it ſpeaks leſs favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably of that which is their Religion, than of that which really is ſo. But I am no way concern'd at it; for I am ſtill of the Opinion, that a Man had as good have no Religion, as ſuch a one as does not conſiſt in <hi>doing Juſtice, loving Mercy, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humbly with our God;</hi> and that a little more
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:95428:4"/>Charity toward thoſe that differ with us about leſſer Matters, will at this time eſpecially do us a great deal more good than all our ſtiff Zeal for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Matters in Controverſy. And it is certainly very injuriouſly done to make the Church of <hi>England</hi> of their Party, when no Perſon can ſpeak with more Moderation, as to thoſe things, than ſhe has done. All that I ſhall further add is, That my Adverſaries would but be ſo juſt to our Church, as to own that the Religion ſhe teaches does conſiſt in Matters of a higher Nature, than a bare ſtickling for our Ceremonies, and that no Man can be a true Church of <hi>England-Man,</hi> who is not more zealous for the Eſſential part of Religion, than the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial: For ſuch an Acknowledgment will give me all the Satisfaction for the Wrong that is done me, that I deſire.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95428:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES Held at NOTTINGHAM, On the <hi>19th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1689.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MICAH 6.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He hath ſhewed thee, O Man, what is good: and what does the Lord thy God require of thee, but to do Juſtly, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS the great and excellent Faculties, with which Human Nature is adorned, do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently demonſtrate that Man is a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Creature; ſo the neceſſity of Religion does plainly appear in this, that all the ſenſitive
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95428:5"/>Enjoyments of this Life, with which the Creatures, that are below us, do reſt ſatisfied, are not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to give ſatisfaction to the deſires of our Nature without it. For take away Religion, and Eating, and Drinking, and all the boaſted Pleaſures of an Animal-Life, will be ſo far from making Life eaſy and comfortable to a Man, that he will labour under infinitely greater wants, than any the ſenſual Perſon can poſſibly complain Religion dooms him to, by forbidding him to humour his Appetite. For we ſhould languiſh under the Diſſatisfactions of our own Minds; and Man by being taught more than the Beaſts of the Earth, and made wiſer than the Fowls of Heaven, would be only wiſe to do Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. Our Underſtanding would be the moſt fatal Inſtrument of our Miſery, and our Wills the great Diſturber of our Peace.</p>
            <p>God therefore has in nothing given us more lively Inſtances of the Goodneſs of his Providence, than in the Methods he has taken to preſerve that which is of ſuch Neceſſity to the Happineſs of Mankind. He knows our Frame, 'tis true, and the Neceſſities of our Nature, and ſince we cannot live without his care of us, he makes thoſe Proviſions for our Fleſh as our Bodily Wants do require: But the great Concern, that exerciſes his Wiſdom and Power, are the Intereſts of Religion, without which he knows all his other Proviſions would do little to make us happy.</p>
            <p>When we conſider indeed how much we our ſelves are concern'd in Religion, it may almoſt ſeem a wonder that a Providence ſhould be needful to preſerve it; that ſince it is ſo abſolutely neceſſary to our preſent Peace and Happineſs, to ſatisfy the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95428:5"/>nobleſt Powers of our Nature, and to prevent thoſe Confuſions that without it we are much more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to than the Creatures that are below us, we ſhould attend to it with ſo much Sollicitude and Care, that even without the watchfulneſs of Divine Providence it ſhould never be ſubject to decay. One would think that a matter, in which we are ſo much intereſted, ſhould lie ſo near our Spirits, and be ſo much upon our Thoughts, that it ſhould never be in danger of being loſt.</p>
            <p>But beſides, that there are watchful Spirits, that with induſtry and Sollicitude endeavour to corrupt and deſtroy it, there is ſo much Corruption in our Nature, and ſo much Ignorance and Folly in our Minds, we have ſo much loſt the true uſe of our Reaſon, and our Spirits are ſo much under the Power of Senſe and the World, that it is with much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, if at any time we raiſe our Minds to the Conſideration of thoſe Things that are ſo much above us; ſo much are our Souls debaſed by conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with ſenſible Objects, that we are apt, upon ſlender Motives, to exchange Truth for Errour; and having once departed from the true Religion, it is no hard matter to ſlide out of a bad one into none at all. So that did not the ſame Providence, that watches over us for our Good, intereſt it ſelf in the Preſervation of Religion, it would long e're this have been as great a Stranger in the World, as the World is to the true Spirit of it. But God, who at firſt planted the Seeds of it in our Nature, has upheld it by ſuch ſtrong Motives and Powerful Arguments, ſuch mighty Miracles, and Signal Providences, as the Reaſon of Man cannot but acknowledg to be the Demonſtrations of the Spirit and of Power.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95428:6"/>
            <p>Thus did he of Old reſtore Religion among the <hi>Jews,</hi> by delivering them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in the promiſed Land: And when, after ſo viſible a Demonſtration of his Power and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they were ſtill apt to revolt from his Service, he awak'd them to a ſenſe of their Duty, by ſetting before them the great Things he had done for them. Thus in the Words before my <hi>Text</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulates with them, ſaying, <hi>O my People, what have I done unto thee? wherein have I wearied thee? Teſtify againſt me. For I brought thee out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and redeemed thee out of the Houſe of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and I ſent before thee</hi> Moſes, Aaron, <hi>and</hi> Miriam. <hi>O my People, remember now what</hi> Balak <hi>King of</hi> Moab <hi>conſulted, and what</hi> Balaam <hi>the Son of</hi> Beor <hi>anſwered him from</hi> Shittim <hi>unto</hi> Gilgal, <hi>that ye may know the Righteouſneſs of the Lord</hi> V. 3, 4, 5. And when by reminding them of thoſe mighty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which were too great to be gainſay'd, and too Powerful to be withſtood, he check'd their ſtraying humour, and put them upon a ſober Enquiry, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal they ſhould come before the Lord, and how them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before the high God.</hi> V. 6. <hi>i.e.</hi> by what means they ſhould appeaſe the Divine Diſpleaſure, and atone for their Crimes: he directs them in the words of my <hi>Text</hi> to ſuch an Expiation, as is of more value, and far more acceptable with God than <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Rams, or ten thouſands of Rivers of Oyl. He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good: and what does the Lord thy God require of thee, but to do Juſtly, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed there is nothing more juſt and equal than that thoſe Motives, whereby God does enforce
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95428:6"/>the true Spirit of Religion upon us, and thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of his Providence whereby he ſecures it to us, ſhould put us upon ſuch Enquiries, <hi>Wherewithal ſhall we come before the Lord, and how our ſelves before the high God?</hi> For when Religion is ſo much our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, he by the Methods he takes to ſecure ſo great a Bleſſing to Mankind, and the wonderful Providences by which he endeavours to call up our Minds from thoſe mean and ſordid Projects, that pinion them to Mortality, and keep them here below, to the Comtemplations of his excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and a lively acknowledgment of his Being, does require that we ſhould <hi>do Juſtice, love Mercy, and walk humbly with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the moſt grateful return we can make to him, for his care in the Preſervation of our neareſt Concernment, he requires that we ſhould apply our Minds to the exerciſe of a moſt vigorous Piety, and the practice of the ſubſtantial Duties of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He has ſhewed thee, O Man, what is good: and what does the Lord thy God require of thee, but to do Juſtly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He has ſhewed thee what is good. Which Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion we may underſtand either of the true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that Religion that he requires of us; or of the powerful Motives to it that he does furniſh us with. That the true Spirit and Life of Religion does not conſiſt in Meats and Drinks, in the dreſs of ſeemingly Spiritual Forms, but in the practice of thoſe weighter matters of the Law, the <hi>doing Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the loving Mercy, and the walking humbly with our God:</hi> And that God has given us the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Motives to excite us to the practice of that Religion that he requires of us.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95428:7"/>
            <p>So that from the Words I ſhall beg leave to ſet before you,
<list>
                  <item>I. The import of that Religion that God requires of us, as it conſiſts in <hi>Juſtice, Mercy, and a walking humbly with our God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. That it is in the practice of theſe Things, that the true Spirit of Religion does conſiſt.</item>
                  <item>III. That the Reaſon, why Men do at any Time act contrary to theſe Things, is, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ignorant of them; For God has ſhewed us what is good.</item>
                  <item>IV. That the practice of theſe Things is highly for our Advantage, and the Benefit of the World: It is the doing what is good.</item>
                  <item>V. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> God does require us to do theſe Things, as he has ſhewed us what is good.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. I am to endeavour to ſet before you the import of the Religion that God requires of us, as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in doing Juſtice, and ſhewing Mercy, and walking humbly with our God. Now Juſtice and Righteouſneſs is frequently taken in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in a very large ſenſe for the ſum of that Duty, which we owe to God; in which ſenſe it extends it ſelf to all the Duties of both Tables. And the Reaſon may be this; becauſe God in reſpect of his being our Creatour has a right of Dominion and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty over us to command us what he pleaſes; which when we refuſe to obſerve, we are unjuſt in diſowning the Right he has to our Obedience: And the obſervance of his Commands is ſtiled, a <hi>doing of Juſtice,</hi> becauſe we then give that Deference to our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95428:7"/>ſupreme Lord as is due to him. Sometimes this Duty is taken in a narrower ſenſe for our doing all thoſe Offices, and diſcharging all thoſe Duties, that we owe to our Neighbour; and in this ſenſe it is limited to the Duties of the ſecond Table. But in its ſtricteſt ſenſe it reſpects only that ſingle vertue which conſiſts in the doing to all Men as we would they ſhould to us, or in the giving to every Man his due. And according to the different Relations, that we ſtand in to each other the Duties that Juſtice obliges us to are various. It requires Inferiours to be Modeſt and Humble; and Superiours courteous and gentle: The People conformable to Laws, and the Magiſtrates ruling in the fear of God. That E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals and Neighbours be kind and condeſcenſive; and all Men govern themſelves by rules of equity in their Dealings, and by thoſe of good Nature in their Converſation: That we walk uprightly, work Righteouſneſs, and ſpeak the Truth from our Hearts. <hi>Render to all their dues,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtome to whom Cuſtome, Fear to whom Fear, and Honour to whom Honour,</hi> Rom. 13.7. In which words the Apoſtle ſums up that Duty and Homage, that Support and Subjection, that Reverence and Obedience, that is owing to the Perſons and Authority of thoſe whom God has ſet over us. And can any thing be more juſt and equal than that we ſhould Honour the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and reverence the Power that protects us? Can any thing be more fit than that we ſhould with the moſt grateful Minds bleſs God for the Patronage of thoſe under whoſe Shadow we live in Safety; and by whoſe Induſtry and Vigilance, Order and peace are preſerved? that we ſhould by a quiet and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95428:8"/>peaceable Deportment make the burden of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as eaſy and light upon their Shoulders as 'tis poſſible, when they really are what they are ſtiled, <hi>Nurſing Fathers to their People, and the Miniſters of God for good?</hi> In a word, that we ſhould bear Faith and true Allegiance to thoſe, to whom we are not only bound by all the ties of Gratitude, but to whom a ſignal Providence has determin'd it, and the Duty we owe to the Society we are Members of, does require it. For if we muſt be allowed to ſuſpend our Duty and Allegiance till the Rights of Princes be determin'd, for ought that I know there are few Societies in the World but muſt of neceſſity break up; ſince there are few Princes can pretend to any better Title than what the Sword and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of their Anceſtours has given them; and ſtill fewer whoſe Poſſeſſion is ſetled upon ſo fair a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation as that of their preſent Majeſties. Was there nothing but Poſſeſſion to be pleaded in the caſe, I do not underſtand but a King of <hi>England</hi> may, by virtue of it, claim our Allegiance as fairly, as either <hi>Auguſtus</hi> or <hi>Nero</hi> did from the Romans. And yet it was with a reſpect to the latter of theſe that St. <hi>Paul</hi> required the Roman Chriſtians to ſubject themſelves becauſe of his Poſſeſſion. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers, for the Powers that are, (i.e.</hi> the Powers that are in being, or that have poſſeſſion of the Crown) <hi>are ordained of God.</hi> Rom. 13. And this our great Caſuiſt Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> has determin'd to be not only Lawful, but a Duty we owe to our ſelves, becauſe it is a madneſs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him that has the Power of the Sword; to our Country, whoſe Peace and Safety we are bound to conſult and take care of; and to him likewiſe that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95428:8"/>does bear the Sword, ſince thereby our Perſons and Fortunes are protected. Neither does he only give us his own; but St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s Judgment in the caſe, who ſo interprets the Apoſtle's Command, <hi>to be ſubject for Conſcience ſake;</hi> as if he had ſaid, ſince every Citizen or Member of a Community is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to himſelf how many benefits he enjoys by the publick Authority, let him know, that as a Recompence for ſo many Advantages, his Obedience is due to him that has the Government.</p>
            <p>But here is not Poſſeſſion alone, but the Conſent of the whole Body of the Kingdom; and I think I may challenge any Prince in the World to ſhew that his Title does ſtand upon a better Foundation.</p>
            <p>The only thing, that can here be objected, that I can think of, is, that we being under a preceding Obligation: to give our Allegiance to the preſent King, is ſo far from being a Matter that in Juſtice we are obliged to, that it is a great piece of Injuſtice to him to whom we have formerly bound our ſelves. And truly I ſhould be apt to think ſo too, had not that unfortunate Prince ſuffer'd himſelf to be ſo far tranſported by the evil Counſels of thoſe, whoſe deſigns could not be carried on but by the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Conſtitution, to invade thoſe Laws by which our Rights are ſecured, and the Meaſures of our Obedience ſtated and bounded. But when he would not be contented with the Obedience that we obliged our ſelves to, but endeavour'd by alienating a principal Part of his Authority, to make us Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to our Conſtitution, by ſubjecting our deareſt Rights to foreign Juriſdiction, thoſe that have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Obedience to the higheſt, have here made a ſtand; and I think 'tis a folly to talk of being bound
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95428:9"/>to give that Obedience which is not only not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, but renounced.</p>
            <p>But it is not only to the Cottages of the Poor that Juſtice is confined; but Kings, and all in Authority, may be reminded, that Subjects have their Rights as well as Kings their Prerogatives; and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing does make a Government more eaſy or grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than the keeping Judgment and doing Juſtice. 'Tis this does adorn the Diadems of Princes, and make the Seats of Judicatures reverenced, as well as feared. Whatever unbounded Power the flattering Diſcourſes of Court-Paraſites have to their own, as well as the Subjects Miſchief, complimented Princes with; <hi>David</hi> was as well skill'd in the extent of a Princes power, and had as much reaſon to be a Friend to the Prerogative as any Man: yet he in his dying words declared (no doubt for the Inſtruction of, and as a Caution to his Son <hi>Solomon</hi>) that <hi>he that ruleth over Men muſt be juſt.</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3. But now if the Power of the Prince be uncontroulable, and para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to all Laws, if the Commands of Authority will warrant our Obedience, though there be ſin in the Command, what need is there of this Caution that they be juſt? <hi>David</hi> was certainly miſtaken in the nature of Government, when he laid this down as an infallible Maxime; for to be ſure he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that their Commands might tranſgreſs the bounds of Juſtice, and by tranſgreſſing their due bounds, degenerate into Tyranny. And indeed all thoſe other Duties that are required of Magiſtrates, <hi>as that they rule in the fear of the Lord; that there be no iniquity with them, no reſpect of Perſons, nor taking of bribes,</hi> are ſo many Limitations to their Power.</p>
            <p>And thus indeed Juſtice it ſelf is limited, when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95428:9"/>we are commanded to ſhew Mercy. For as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and uſeful a Vertue as Juſtice is, it becomes an intolerable Grievance by being exceſſive. And therefore the Wiſe Man requires us <hi>not to be Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous over-much.</hi> Eccl. 7.16. not to be too rigorous in the vindicating our own Rights, nor in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Laws upon the Offenders; much leſs to ſtrain the Laws beyond their due bounds and true meaning; or the making uſe of them for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing a Party that thwarts a corrupt Deſign. For though it is fit that every Man ſhould be juſt to himſelf; yet it is by no means fit that any Man ſhould croſs the tender Inſtincts of his Nature, which are Humanity, Mercy and Compaſſion. Though it is fit that the Authority and Reputation of Government be upheld; yet is by no means fit, that ſo ſacred a thing as Authority ſhould be made vile by unmanly Paſſions, or ſo noble a Vertue as Juſtice proſtituted to baſe Ends. <hi>To love Mercy, and to do good, are Sacrifices wherewith God and Men are well pleaſed:</hi> And 'tis much better to err on the mild and compaſſionate ſide, than by over-rigorous Juſtice to approach too near the bounds of Cruelty. 'Tis then only that Juſtice does ſtand in the beſt light, and appear with the greateſt Juſter, when it is ſhadowed with Humanity, and qualified with Mercy.</p>
            <p>But yet to make it the more lovely, it muſt be founded upon the more noble Principle of <hi>walking humbly with our God.</hi> For 'tis this that will lay thoſe violent Paſſions, that are apt to tranſport us beyond the true bounds of Moderation and Judgment. 'Tis this will make us obſerve and follow the tenderneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our Nature, and teach us that Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Mercy is the nobleſt Embelliſhment of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95428:10"/>Juſtice. 'Tis this will make us over-look ſmall Faults, and be apt to forgive, or take up with moderate Satisfactions for great ones. The <hi>Syriac</hi> Verſion renders it, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſis paratus ad ſequendum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum Deum tuum,</hi> that thou beeſt ready to follow or to walk in the Steps of the Lord thy God, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him in the ſlowneſs of his wrath, and in that Mercy that he thinks of in the midſt of Judgment. Or if we take the words as they ſtand in our Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they preſcribe a Vertue not only becoming us as we are Sinners, and in regard of the tranſcendent Majeſty of the God of Heaven, but moſt apt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate thoſe rigorous Exceſſes of Juſtice, that do ill become our Nature. For he that is humbled by the ſenſe of that Juſtice he has provok'd, and that Mercy that he ſtands in need of, will not take his Fellow-Servant by the Throat for every petty Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or inconſiderable Debt, when he conſiders that he has a vaſt one of his own either to ſatisfy or to be forgiven. Theſe are Vertues of ſo brave a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that without them we can neither pretend to our Nature nor our Religion. For,</p>
            <p n="2">II. 'Tis in the practice of theſe things that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion does conſiſt. Whatever leſs than theſe things we place Religion in, we not only rudely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front it, but our own Nature. Although the Jewiſh Religion did not only allow, but oblige that People to external Obſervances, and for the main of it conſiſt in Sacrifices and other viſible Rites; yet the reaſon why God did inſtitute a Religion of this Nature for them, was not becauſe it is the beſt in its own nature and moſt agreeable to the Divine perfections, but becauſe it was the beſt for them.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95428:10"/>But yet in after-Ages, when the rudeneſs of their Minds began to wear off, he by degrees did incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to them that Religion that was more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him than their moſt pompous Service. <hi>Wherewithal ſhall I come before the Lord, and how my ſelf before the high God? Shall I come before him with burnt Offerings, with Calves of a year old? Will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſands of Rams, or with ten thouſands of Rivers of Oyl? ſhall I give my firſt-born for my tranſgreſſion, the fruit of my Body for the Sin of my Soul?</hi> Theſe were Enquiries that a Jew, whoſe Religion did exact from him pompous and viſible Expiations, might make. But however God dreſs'd up a Religion of this Nature for him, yet he tells him by his Prophet, that <hi>to do Juſtice, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with God,</hi> are things more becoming humane Nature, and more grateful to the divine. 'Tis certain indeed that Religion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be among Men, without ſome kind of dreſs; and the more decent and comely it is, the more grateful does it appear to the Eyes of Men. But yet, if while we tithe <hi>Mint, Annis</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> we neglect the weightier matters of the Law, <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Faith;</hi> if while we eagerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for doubtful Opinions, and external Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, we are unconcern'd for the <hi>doing Juſtice,</hi> the <hi>loving Mercy,</hi> and <hi>the walking humbly with our God,</hi> we repreſent Religion as ſo poor and lank a thing as the reaſon of man cannot poſſibly ſtoop to. The exerciſes of Piety toward God, and Juſtice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity toward our Neighbour, are ſuch lofty and ſublime Matters, that an underſtand Creature is eaſily reconciled to a great and venerable Opinion of them; But a Religion that conſiſts only in Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95428:11"/>Shows and Pompous Pageantries, in things that only exerciſe the Body and pleaſe the Senſe, is fitter for a Beaſt, that can look no further than to Objects of Senſe, than a Man, than is capable of ſublime and ſpiritual Entertainments. Though therefore Religion cannot well be performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome kind of Rites, yet the fewer they are the better; becauſe the leſs there is in Religion to pleaſe our Senſes, the more will our Minds be at liberty to attend to thoſe Spiritual Objects, and the exerciſe of thoſe Divine Vertues wherein the Life of it does conſiſt.</p>
            <p>I will not enter upon the diſpute, whether the Rites of our Church be ſo many, and of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as will juſtify any one in ſeparating from it; for that will carry me much further, and require more time than a diſcourſe upon this Occaſion will permit, or allow me: But this methinks I may ſay, that ſince the difference between us is only about In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Things, and our unhappy Diviſions have of late like to have undone us; a little more Zeal for Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Chriſtian Charity, and ſomething leſs on both ſides for thoſe things that are not to be weighed againſt them, would as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our Prudence as 'tis neceſſary for our Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. I come now,</p>
            <p n="3">III. To the third thing I propounded; which is, That the reaſon why Men at any time act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theſe ſubſtantial Duties of Religion, is not becauſe they are ignorant of them. If Men deny either God, or their Neighbours their due, and either impiouſly affront their Maker, or injuriouſly diſquiet their Fellow-Creature; If any baſely fell
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95428:11"/>themſelves to work wickedneſs, and by all the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Fraud and Cunning, or the ruder attempts of Violence and Wrong, endeavour to break down all the ſences of Right and Property: If Equals diſturb each others Poſſeſſions, and by Wrongs and Injuries lay the Foundation of vexatious Law-ſuits; If Men by open Force, or ſecret Fraud endeavour to over-power or undermine each other, and there be complainings in our Streets by reaſon of the Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Fraudulent, or the Violence of the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour; If at any time we behold that which the Wiſe-Man did, <hi>viz. The tears of ſuch as are oppreſſed, and that they have no Comforter, but that on the ſide of the Oppreſſor there is Power.</hi> Eccl. 4.1. If Subjects by their murmurs and Complaints render the moſt eaſy Government grievous to themſelves, and to thoſe that God has entruſted it with; or Princes not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with that juſt Power, that would make them beloved of their People and dreaded by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, do fall to digging up Foundations and over-turning Conſtitutions, that out of the ruines of their Peoples Liberties they may erect a Babel of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Arbitrary Power; This, I ſay, is not to be reſolved into their Ignorance of the Juſtice and Mercy that God and Nature do teach and require. No, No, God has ſhewed us what is good; and if we will do that which is bad, it is becauſe we live by other Rules than thoſe of Religion, and govern our ſelves by other Intereſt than thoſe of our preſent or future Happineſs. Men to ſilence the clamours of an untoward Conſcience may perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they do not know they do amiſs, when they do ſuch things. But are we ſuch Strangers to God, or our ſelves? Are the Commands of God to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95428:12"/>keep Judgment and to do Juſtice, to work Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and to do that which is juſt and right, ſo few or obſcure? Are the promiſes of his Favour to thoſe that do theſe things, and his threats of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Vengeance againſt thoſe that practice o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, ſo much hid from our Eyes? No, No; God has ſhewed us what is good: and if Men do not do <hi>Juſtice,</hi> nor <hi>ſhew Mercy,</hi> it is becauſe their Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Covetouſneſs, their Luſts or their Paſſions do influence them. But yet how ſtrongly ſo ever theſe Vices do prevail in us, and how ſturdy ſo ever thoſe Prejudices are that they create, when they do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail; there is enough in the nature of theſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to tempt even a very bad Man to the practice of them, if he would conſider them.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The practice of them is highly for our own Advantage, and the publick Intereſt. <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs exalteth a Nation,</hi> ſaith the Wiſe-man: It does ſo, not only as it procures the mighty Fame of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Underſtanding to a People; which <hi>Moſes</hi> told the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> would be the great advantage of their Piety, and ſtrict obſervance of their Laws, <hi>Keep therefore, and do them: for this is your Wiſdom, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in the ſight of the Nations, which ſhall hear all theſe Statutes, and ſay, Surely this great Nation is a wiſe and underſtanding People.</hi> Deut. 4.6. But as it makes Human Societies ſtrong and firmly united, neither in danger of being broken by inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Diviſions, nor deſtroyed by foreign Enemies. When the Spirit of Religion does run through all the parts of a Nation, it becomes vigorous and lively; and like the Body-Natural when Nature is ſtrong, free from apprehenſions of a Diſſolution:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95428:12"/>But for want of Religion it grows ſo full of groſs and ill Humours, that it languiſhes and decays in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly, and, without an Enemy to give the fatal Blow, is ready to expire of it ſelf. But there are two things eſpecially, in which the great advantage of Religion, as it conſiſts in Piety toward God, and in Juſtice and Mercy toward Men, will appear.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That without it the World cannot be kept in any tolerable good Condition.</item>
               <item>2. That without it we cannot have any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able hope to ſee Things ſettle well again, when once out of Order.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Without it the World cannot be kept in any tolerable good Condition. The Exigencies of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature, and the Defects, if not the ill uſe of Human Wiſdom, do make it neceſſary that the World ſhould be under ſo great Wiſdom and Power as that of the Almighty. And ſince it is only Piety that can engage the Divine Favour and Protection towards us, what a World of Miſchief muſt we bring upon our ſelves, if by neglect thereof we provoke him to withdraw his Providence from us? If we overlook our own Infirmities and Sins; and demean our ſelves before him with ſo much Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs and Pride, as if we ſtood not in need either of his Power to ſupport, or his Mercy to pardon, we juſtly provoke him to let us ſee our Vanity by leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to our own Wiſdom and Prudence.</p>
            <p>And was there no ſuch thing as Juſtice or Mercy in the World, there could be no Amity nor Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, no Peace, and conſequently no Society. Man to Man would be more ſavage than Brutes, and the World an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> or Field of Blood and Confuſion. There would be no Obedience paid to the lawful
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95428:13"/>Commands of Magiſtrates, no Defence and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction afforded to Subjects; no Reſpect nor Reverence to Superiours, nor Courteſy and Affability to Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, no Kindneſs nor Familiarity among Equals; no Mercy or Compaſſion to thoſe in Diſtreſs, nor Tenderneſs of each others Concerns; no Regard to Promiſes or Contracts, to Oaths or the ſtrongeſt Obligations; but every Man would be at liberty to make the beſt uſe of Power and Opportunity for the advancing his own Fortune. Conſcience would be an empty Name, Intereſt the only ruling Principle and every action lawful that conduced to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing a Deſign. For without Juſtice, nothing would be a Man's Duty; and without Mercy, no Benefit could be expected from Society: but all thoſe Fences wherewith Religion does bound Mens Appetites and Paſſions would be thrown down, and all thoſe bands that tye their Hands and Tongues broken. So that Mens Hearts would be fradulent and deceitful, their Throats an open Sepulchre, and the Poyſon of Aſps under their Lips. Their Mouths would be full of Curſing and Bitterneſs, their Teeth Spears and Arrows, and their Tongues ſharp Swords: Their Words might be ſmooth but falſe, their Feet ſwift to ſhed Blood, their Hands ready to execute any villanous Deſign, and all the Members of their Bodies Inſtruments of Unrighteouſneſs. This would be the ſad ſtate that the want of Juſtice and Mercy would reduce Societies to, and God by creating Man a Sociable Creature would have done infinitely worſe for him than if he had only made him an Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of a Wilderneſs. That Appetite, which he deſign'd for the great Bleſſing and Ornament of his Nature, would have proved his Curſe, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95428:13"/>occaſion of more Miſery than all that the Beaſts of the Field are ſubject to: Neither could any thing remedy this Evil but the reſtoring of Juſtice and Mercy to the World. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis not poſſible the World, when diſorder'd, ſhould ſettle again without them. 'Tis only theſe Vertues can make Society deſirable, and the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Neighbour beneficial to us. In all the Diſtempers of the Body-Natural, the Cure is wrought by removing the Cauſe; and till that be done, the Body will languiſh in ſpight of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, or the Strength of Cordials. And unleſs the ſame courſe be taken in the Diſtempers of Civil-Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, 'tis not to be expected to ſee them return to their former ſtrong and vigorous State. They will continue ſickly and weak ſo long as thoſe ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours do overburthen it, which are not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged but by <hi>doing Juſtice, ſhewing Mercy, and walking humbly with our God.</hi> For by a ſincere Piety the Wiſdom of God is engaged to preſide over, and direct thoſe Counſels, which without it muſt of neceſſity be confuſed and diſtracted; and Divine Providence, without which Miſchief comes upon Miſchief, Rumour upon Rumour, <hi>and Men ſeek Peace but find none,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks, returns to the helm, that it hath forſaken; and ſafely conducts ſo penitent a People out of the Intricacies and Mazes they were loſt in.</p>
            <p>And by Juſtice and Mercy Mens Minds are freed from thoſe Jealouſies and Diſtruſts, that the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Vices do occaſion. By being juſt, Mens Minds are ſet at eaſe from thoſe Apprehenſions, that fill them with Anguiſh and Convulſions; and by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mercy, we feel the benefits of Society, and that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95428:14"/>it is good for us that we were fitted for it. For when we have nothing to fear, but a great deal to hope for from our being united into civil Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, then Friendſhip and Charity do ſo ſtrongly cement them, that it is not in the Power of Men or Devils to ſhake or endanger them. It is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the uſual Method of thoſe who project the ruine of a State, is by ſtraitning and limiting the publick Juſtice, to create Parties; and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Humanity and Mercy, to heighten Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities: And the only way to heal a diſtemper'd State, is to remove thoſe Mounds and Works, that have thrown Injuſtice with too much weight and ſeverity upon one ſide, while the other has ſeem'd to be tolerated to do miſchief; and to put on thoſe Bowels of Mercy and Compaſſion which will blunt the edg of the keeneſt Rage, and reconcile the moſt divided Spirits. For then will our <hi>Peace be as a River, when Righteouſneſs does run down as the Waves of the Sea, and Mercy and Truth do meet together.</hi> And as theſe Vertues are of ſo great advantage to the World; So,</p>
            <p n="5">V. God has taken care to recommend them to our practice, by ſhewing us what is good. He has ſhewed us what is good, as by our reaſonable Nature he has fitted us for Society; which, as long as Juſtice and Mercy do flouriſh, will afford us mighty helps and advantages for the promoting our Affairs. In this he has advanced our Nature above the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe wild and ſavage Creatures, that howl in Wilderneſſes, and creep into holes and caves of the Earth. In this he has done us ſo much good, that 'tis but little more that he has done for the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95428:14"/>Angels, thoſe glorious Inhabitants of the City of the living God. And ſince God has ſhewed us this good, is it not highly reaſonable that we ſhould live up to the Primitive intention of our Creatour, and take care of thoſe great advantages that he has put into our Hands? Is it not fit that we ſhould conſult our own Intereſt, and make as much of that Good that God has ſhewn us as poſſibly we may? In this then God does recommend Juſtice and Mercy to our Practice, as he has planted ſuch an Appetite in us as can no ways be ſatisfied without them.</p>
            <p>But, bleſſed be his Name, he has furniſhed us with another Motive, as in the late wonderful and unexpected Revolution, he has to a Miracle ſhewed us what is good. For he has revived our Laws which began viſibly to languiſh and faint un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dreadful weight of a diſpencing Power; and has preſerved our Religion, that requires us to <hi>do Juſtice, to ſhew Mercy, and to walk humbly with our God,</hi> from the overflowings of Superſtition and Idolatry; and our Conſtitution from the ſecret Underminings and open Attempts of an Arbitrary Deſpotick Government: He has taken the Crafty in their own Counſels, and turned thoſe that had the reputation of the greateſt States-Men, backwards: He, I ſay, when all places were full of Fears and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Apprehenſions, and all Faces gather'd black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the dread of thoſe Evils that were ready to break in upon us; when Juſtice was made a dead weight to link and oppreſs thoſe that durſt be true and faithful to the Intereſts of their Country, and the Mercies of Men were cruel; when the Will of a Prince that had unhappily given himſelf up to the conduct of Prieſts and Jeſuits, was the ſole Director
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95428:15"/>of the Bench, and Judgments were given without any Rule or Meaſure, but the Intereſts of a Party, who depended more upon Oppreſſion and Violence for the carrying on their Deſigns, than either the goodneſs of their Cauſe, or the ſtrength of their Arguments; He, I ſay, when our Religion, our laws, and Liberties, all the dear Concernments both of this Life and that which is to come, were doom'd to perpetual bondage, under Popery, and Arbitrary Power, was pleas'd to raiſe us up a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, who hath done great things for us, for which we and Generations after us have cauſe to rejoyce, and to bleſs the Lord.</p>
            <p>Had any Man told us ſome Months before God wrought this great Deliverance for us, that he had ſeen our Affliction, and heard our Cry, and would come down to deliver us in ſo eaſy and cheap a way as that which we have ſeen, would not his Words have ſeem'd to us, as the firſt notice of Chriſt's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection did to his Diſciples, like idle Tales? But tho we were like them that dream, when the Lord turned our Captivity, yet we ought not to be ſo ſtill, when we reap the Fruits and enjoy the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of ſo great a Bleſſing. No, God has ſhewed us what is good, he has put us under an eaſy, and truly Engliſh Government, a Government that knows no Rule but our Laws, nor no other End but the Peace and Proſperity of our Country, the Safeguard and Protection of our Perſons, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our Rights and Liberties, and above all the Encouragement of Vertue, and the uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Proteſtant Intereſt; and <hi>what now does the Lord our God require of us, but to do Juſtice, to love Meroy, and to walk humbly with our God?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:95428:15"/>
            <p>This is that Return that he expects from us for ſo great a Bleſſing; that Return that in gratitude we are obliged to make, and which will fully compleat our Deliverance. For then will our Enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of ever ſeeing their Deſigns upon us compaſſed, when they ſee our Diſtractions healed, our Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities laid, and the Hearts of Engliſh-Men united by Love and Friendſhip. Then will their Malice find no matter to work upon, nor no Party whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents ſhall furniſh them with means to engage them in deſigns againſt the Intereſts of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and their Country. Then we need no more fear the Arts of Jeſuites, nor the Power of <hi>France.</hi> For nothing can deſtroy <hi>England</hi> but its being crumbled into Parties; and nothing will contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute more to the removing all Diſcontents, and the extirpating that Bitterneſs which has of late ſo much ſhook the Foundations of our Peace, as that <hi>Juſtice, Mercy, and humble walking with God,</hi> that will make God a Friend to Man, and every Man as a God to his Neighbour. For who is he that will harm us, if we be followers of that which is good? Who is it that we need to fear, if from the ſenſe of the good that God has ſhown us we learn to walk more humbly with him, and by a more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious regard to Piety engage him to be our Guardian and Protector? Nay who will dare to attempt upon our Peace, if they ſee that we dwell under the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the Almighty, and ſee us as wiſe to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine their deſigns by acts of Juſtice, Mercy and Humanity, as they are to proſecute them by firſt ſowing Diviſions, and then exaſperating them by leavening Mens Souls with a Spirit of Oppreſſion and Violence, Inhumanity and Cruelty? They
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95428:16"/>could never have put us into ſo much dread, had not our own unhappy Heats prepared them Parties, who for wreaking a little Spight, eaſily, as they were complemented, cloſed in with the advantage of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing countenanced at Court: And there is nothing that for the future will ſo perfectly remove our Fears, as that Juſtice and Mercy that will unite our Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, and reconcile our Hearts. For how is it poſſible there ſhould be Heats and Animoſities among Men, when no Man has any cauſe of Apprehenſions from another? How ſhall any Man converſe with Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe or Jealouſy, when he knows of none that will do him harm? So long as Juſtice is the governing Principle among Men, Superiours need not fear any ill from their Inferiours; becauſe this Vertue will incline them to give them all Honour and Reverence that is their due: Nor need Inferiours have any dread of the Power of thoſe above them; becauſe this Vertue joined with Mercy will diſpoſe them to uſe it for their Defence: And no Man need to have a Guard upon himſelf, for fear of any Perſon he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes with; becauſe every Man will be kind and good-natured. Then will our Seats of Judicature be reverenced. And ſince it is impoſſible but ſuch Differences will ariſe among the moſt honeſt and juſt Perſons, as can no otherwiſe be determined but in a Court of Judicature; then no Man will be afraid of ſubmitting his Cauſe to the Judgment of a Court, when both Witneſſes and Jurors do fear an Oath, and give their Teſtimonies and their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts according to Truth and Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And O that in this our Day, in which God by having ſhewn us what is good, does ſeem to put us upon the trial, whether we will do our ſelves good;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95428:16"/>and in which, from the Example of a pious and good Prince, we have all the Encouragements that a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can deſire to Piety, Juſtice and Charity, we would ſtudy to know theſe things, that make ſo much for our Peace and happineſs. For the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of which great Bleſſing, may it pleaſe the God of Mercy and Love to give us the Grace and Wiſdom to apply our Minds to know the import and advantage of thoſe great Vertues of Piety, Juſtice and Mercy, which, for the good he has ſhown us, he requires of us, for the Sake of his beloved Son, and our gracious Mediatour and Redeemer; To whom with thee, O Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all Honour and Glory, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
